Business Administration

COLLEGE: Business Administration

MAJOR: Business Administration

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Business Administration

HOURS REQUIRED: 120 hours for degree (21 hours for the major)

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.5 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes–for non business students only

CHIEF ADVISER: D’vee Buss

DESCRIPTION

The business administration major is designed for students who wish to obtain a broad education in business administration rather than specializing in a specific area within the College. Under this option, students may choose courses from any of the departments within the College in any combination. For the student who has an educational goal that bridges two or more areas of business, the general business administration major permits the design of a tailor-made program to fit that goal.

Many organizations seek generalists rather than specialists when hiring employees. Some employers feel that in today’s world of rapid change, individuals who have a broad educational background are more adaptive to this change and are better suited to a variety of roles within the organization.

ADMISSION

Major/Department Admission

Admission requirements for all majors in the College are the same as those for University Admission as noted under UNL General Admission Requirements.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Core Requirements

In addition to the College Degree Requirements, students will complete 21 hours of course work for the major.

As noted in the College Degree Requirements section, all course work for the major must be taken for a grade.

No departmental 399/499 courses may count toward the business administration major

Specific Major Requirements

Business Core Advanced–Major (BCA-M)

Requirements for students interested in pursuing the bachelor of science degree with a major in business administration will complete 21 hours of 300/400-level business course work for the Business Core Advanced-Major (BCA-M) to be selected from course work offered by:

Accounting

Economics

Finance

Management

Marketing

As part of the 21 hour requirement:

Course work must be from the 300/400-level.
A MINIMUM of three departments must be represented.
A MINIMUM of 9 hours must be taken at the 400 level.
A MAXIMUM of 9 hours from one department may count toward the major.
NBR 6–ACE 9 – ECON 321; MNGT 365, MNGT 428 can be double counted to fulfill NBR 6–ACE 9 and course work for the major.
ECON 321 or MNGT 428 may also be counted for the IBCR
In any option where double counting is permitted, only 3 hours of credit are used; student must still meet the 120 hour requirement for the degree.
In any option where double counting is permitted for NBR requirements and the major, course work cannot, in turn, be used for any minor.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Prerequisite Requirements/Rules

Enrollment in any upper-level course work offered by the departments requires completion of appropriate prerequisites. Refer to course descriptions for specific course prerequisites.

Grade Rules

C- and D Grades

Same as College grade rules.

Pass/No Pass Limits

Same as College Pass/No Pass limits.

GPA Requirements

Same as College GPA requirements.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Business Administration Minor – for Non Business Students Only

The College of Business Administration has joined with the College of Arts and Sciences, the College of Engineering, and the Hixson-Lied College of Fine and Performing Arts to offer a minor in general business to NON BUSINESS STUDENTS ONLY to provide these students a general business background. Students who minor in general business and are accepted into a masters program offered through the College of Business Administration will find they are well prepared to enter the masters program. Students in colleges other than those noted above should check with their college about the availability of the business minor for that specific college. The requirements remain the same.

Pass/No Pass. All course work for the minor (except BSAD 150) must be taken for a grade.

GPA. Please note: “most” course work for the minor requires a 2.5 cumulative GPA.

Prerequisites. ARE enforced and there are no exceptions or waivers of this policy.

Non-Business Course Requirements

Complete these two courses early on as they are prerequisites for most other courses for the minor

MATH 104 Calculus for Managerial & Social Sciences (3 hrs) or higher level calculus (MATH 106, MATH 107, MATH 208)
BSAD 150 Business Computer Applications (1 hr not applicable to degree)

Business Foundation Course Requirements

ACCT 201 & ACCT 202 Introductory Accounting I & II (3 hrs ea) or ACCT 306 Survey of Accounting (4 hrs) (Must have approval to take ACCT 306.)
ECON 211 & ECON 212 Principles of Macro & Microeconomics (3 hrs each)
ECON 215 Statistics (See prerequisites to enroll.) (3 hrs)

Business Intermediate Course Requirements

Most of the following courses require completion of the prerequisites listed above; refer to specific course descriptions for restrictions on enrollment:

FINA 361 Finance (3 hrs)
MRKT 341 Marketing (3 hrs)
Select one from the following: (3 hrs)

MNGT 350/MIST 350 Intro to Management Information Systems

MNGT 320 Principles of Management

MNGT 331 Operations & Supply Chain Management

MNGT 360 Managing Behavior in Organizations

300/400-level business course (3 hrs)

Total for the Minor (28-32 hrs)

Any exceptions or alternative courses for substitutions to these requirements, must be submitted in writing to the Academic Planning Committee of the College for acceptance. See someone in CBA 138 for filing the appropriate appeal paperwork.

OTHER

All students enrolling in CBA courses are required to meet the prerequisites listed for each course, including any specific grade or GPA requirement, to include junior standing, as well as expected completion of the BCF and BCI for enrollment in most 300 or 400-level business courses. This includes the required course work information systems, communications, mathematics and statistics, accounting, and economics requirements as well as marketing, finance, production, MIS, human resources, and business law prior to enrolling in course work for their major.

Dietetics

COLLEGE: Education & Human Sciences

DEPARTMENT: Nutrition & Health Sciences

PROGRAM: Dietetics (Didactic Program in Dietetics)

DEGREE: Bachelor of Science in Education & Human Sciences

HOURS REQUIRED: 120

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

CHIEF ADVISER: Judith Hofeldt

DESCRIPTION

The Dietetics (Didactic Program in Dietetics) option is designed for students who wish to become registered dietitians and practitioners in clinical, community, food industry, and foodservice areas of nutrition. Registered dietitians are employed by hospitals, community agencies, and various government or private organizations. The University of Nebraska Didactic Program in Dietetics is currently granted accreditation status by the Commission on Accreditation for Dietetics Education of the American Dietetic Association, 120 South Riverside Plaza, Suite 2000, Chicago, IL 60606-6995, 312/899-0040, ext. 5400. Completion of degree requirements will result in the student being awarded a Verification Statement of Completion of the Didactic Program in Dietetics. Following completion of the Didactic Program in Dietetics, an accredited dietetic internship program is required before students are eligible to take the registration examination and obtain the Registered Dietitian (RD) credential.

Acceptance into an accredited dietetic internship program is competitive. Currently, there is a significant shortage of available internship positions for the number of students applying for acceptance into an internship program. Acceptance into an internship program cannot be guaranteed.

All required accreditation information can be found at http://cehs.unl.edu/nhs/undergrad/dietetics.shtml.

ADMISSION

Application to the Didactic Program in Dietetics (DPD)

Following successful completion (a grade of C or above must be earned in all NUTR courses) of prerequisite courses*, application is necessary for entrance into the Didactic Program in Dietetics (DPD) which consists primarily of nutrition course work at the 300 and 400 level.

Program Acceptance Requirements

(See adviser in Student Advising Center and/or DPD Student Handbook for complete details.)

1. Application must be submitted by February 15 prior to the fall semester of desired acceptance.

2. Admission requirements for acceptance into the Didactic Program in Dietetics include a cumulative grade point average of 3.0 or above and completion of 48 or more credit hours which must include the following prerequisite courses (courses can be in progress):

CHEM 109 General Chemistry I & CHEM 110 General Chemistry II

BIOS 101 & BIOS 101L General Biology & Lab or BIOS 102 Cell Structure & Function or BIOS 103 Organismic Biology

NUTR 100 Nutrition, Exercise & Health

NUTR 150 Foundation in Nutrition & Health Promotion

NUTR 244 & NUTR 245 Scientific Principles of Food Preparation & Lab

NUTR 250 Human Nutrition & Metabolism

NUTR 251 Nutrition Through the Life Cycle

NUTR 253 Cultural Aspects of Food & Nutrition

Verification Statement of Meeting Didactic Program in Dietetics Requirements

The Department of Nutrition and Health Sciences will provide a Verification Statement of a student meeting Didactic Program in Dietetics (DPD) requirements based on the program in effect in the Undergraduate Bulletin the student is using for graduation requirements if the student is continuously enrolled and graduates within five years. If the student cannot finish their studies within this five-year time period, they must comply with the didactic program reflected in the Undergraduate Bulletin currently in effect. The Department of Nutrition and Health Sciences will not accept course work to meet prerequisite courses for DPD program admission or DPD requirements from any university or college outside the University of Nebraska system in which a grade of D-, D, or D+ was earned.

In order to receive a Verification Statement of a student meeting Didactic Program in Dietetic requirements, a minimum of 15 credits from 300- or 400-level courses must be completed at the University of Nebraska–Lincoln. Nine of the 15 credit hours must come from three of the following classes: NUTR 450 Medical Nutrition Therapy I, NUTR 452 and NUTR 452L Medical Nutrition Therapy II and Lab, NUTR 455 Advanced Nutrition, or NUTR 473 Organization and Administration of Foodservice.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Core Requirements

DPD Entrance Requirements (22 hrs)

CHEM 109 General Chemistry I (4 hrs)

CHEM 110 General Chemistry II (4 hrs)

BIOS 101 & BIOS 101L General Biology & Lab or BIOS 102 Cell Structure & Function or BIOS 103 Organismic Biology (hours met in ACE)

NUTR 100 Nutrition, Exercise & Health (3 hrs)

NUTR 150 Foundations in Nutrition & Health Promotion (1 hr)

NUTR 244 & NUTR 245 Scientific Principles of Food Preparation & Lab (4 hrs)

NUTR 250 Human Nutrition & Metabolism (3 hrs)

NUTR 251 Nutrition Through the Life Cycle (3 hrs)

NUTR 253 Cultural Aspects of Food & Nutrition (hours met in ACE)

Specific Major Requirements

Professional Requirements (51-55 hrs)

Nutrition and Health Sciences (32 hrs)

Only grades of C or above will count toward graduation requirements for NUTR courses.

NUTR 344 Food & Nutrition for Healthy Living (3 hrs)

NUTR 356 Nutrition Education in the Community (3 hrs)

NUTR 370 Food Production Management (3 hrs)

NUTR 371 Applied Food Production Lab (1 hrs)

NUTR 402 Facts & Fiction in Fitness & Food (3 hrs)

NUTR 450 Medical Nutrition Therapy I (3 hrs)

NUTR 452 Medical Nutrition Therapy II (3 hrs)

NUTR 452L Medical Nutrition Therapy II Lab (1 hrs)

NUTR 453 Nutrition & Fitness Communication Strategies (3 hrs)

NUTR 455 Advanced Nutrition (3 hrs)

NUTR 470 Cost Control for Foodservice (2 hrs)

NUTR 473 Organization & Administration of Foodservice (3 hrs)

NUTR 490 Professional Preparation for Careers in Dietetics (1 hrs)

Supporting Courses (4-7 hrs)

CEHS 200 Families, Schools, & Communities (hours met in ACE)

EDPS 459 Statistical Methods or STAT 218 Intro to Statistics (hours met in ACE)

PSYC 181 Intro to Psychology (4 hrs)

MATH 101 College Algebra or higher, trigonometry or calculus (MATH requirement waived if placed above MATH 101 on Math Placement Exam) (0-3 hrs)

Supporting Sciences (15-16 hrs)

BIOS 111 The Biology of Microoganisms or BIOS 312 & BIOS 314 Fundamentals of Microbiology & Lab or NUTR 372 Food Safety & Sanitation (3-4 hrs)

BIOS 213 & BIOS 213L Human Physiology & Lab or ASCI 240 Anatomy & Physiology of Domestic Animals (4 hrs)

CHEM 251 & CHEM 253 Organic Chemistry I & Lab (4 hrs)

BIOC 321 & BIOC 321L Elements of Biochemistry & Lab or BIOC 431 Biomolecules & Metabolism (4 hrs)

Electives (11-16 hrs)

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Grade Rules

Grades Earned at UNL, UNO, UNK

Grades of D-, D, D+, C- satisfy requirements of the programs in human sciences unless specified otherwise under the Programs and Departments section of the bulletin. Students who receive a grade of D-, D, D+, or C-, however, are encouraged to retake the course, particularly if it is in the major area.

Grades Earned Outside UN System

Up to 9 hours of grades below C (C-, D+, D, D-) from other academic institutions can only be applied to general education requirements and elective classes.

Policy for Pass/No Pass Courses

The Pass/No Pass (P/N) option is designed for students who want to study elective areas or topics when they may have minimum preparation. If used for this purpose, the option can enrich the student’s academic experience without lowering the student’s grade point average. Free electives may be taken P/N. Students can earn no more than 12 hours of pass credit excluding courses offered on Pass/No Pass only basis. Not all classes can be taken under the Pass/No Pass option. All courses, specified by course and number, must be taken for a grade. Should a student have earned a P in one of the courses prior to starting the option, the P will be reviewed by the appropriate department.

Economics (ASC)

COLLEGE: Arts & Sciences

MAJOR: Economics

DEGREES OFFERED: Bachelor of Arts or Bachelor of Science

HOURS REQUIRED: 125

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

CHIEF ADVISER: Roger Butters

DESCRIPTION

Chair: Scott M. Fuess, Jr., 340 College of Business Administration Building

Professors: Anderson, Cushing, Edwards, Fuess, Hayden, MacPhee, May, Rosenbaum, Schmidt, van den Berg, Walstad

Associate Professors: Allgood, Kim, McGarvey, Thompson

Assistant Professors: Butters, Giertz

Assistant Professor of Practice: Asarta

NOTE for economic majors: Completion of ECON 311 and ECON 312 is recommended before taking other 300- and 400-level courses.

Economic analysis is useful in many decisions made by individuals, businesses, nonprofit organizations, and governments. In addition to opportunities in teaching, economists are employed in many branches of government and on the staffs of corporations in manufacturing, insurance, banking, brokerage and other financial services. Economists often serve as consultants, either individually or in consulting firms. Today’s economists deal with problems ranging from monetary and fiscal policy, monopoly and competition, environmental improvement, labor relations, regional development, urban reconstruction, economic development and international business and finance. Economics is also a popular major for students planning to enter professional and graduate programs, particularly in law, foreign service, labor relations, or business administration.

The department of economics offers the opportunity for intensive study in 11 specialized economic areas: economic theory, comparative economic and regional development, econometrics, economic education, economic history, industrial organization and regulation, international trade and finance, institutional economics, labor economics, monetary economics, and public finance.

Order of Studies. Students who plan to take only one year of economics are advised to take ECON 211 and ECON 212, or ECON 210 and a 300-level course in economics. These courses would satisfy the 6 hr Essential Studies requirement. Either ECON 211 and ECON 212 or ECON 210 are prerequisite to most of the courses in the department. Students who major in economics will find it advantageous to take ECON 211 and ECON 212 in their sophomore year.

Graduate Work. The advanced degrees of master of arts and doctor of philosophy are offered. For details of these programs see the Graduate Studies Bulletin.

This department participates in the program for International Studies. For a full description of the program, see “International Studies.”

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Specific Major Requirements

An economics major must complete 30 credit hours of economics. These 30 hours must include:

Hours

ECON 211 Principles of Macroeconomics 3

ECON 212 Principles of Microeconomics 3

ECON 215 Statistics* 3

ECON 311 Intermediate Macroeconomics 3

ECON 312 Intermediate Microeconomics 3

Economics 300- or 400-level courses 6

Economics 400-level courses 9

Total 30

*NOTE for economics majors: STAT 218 may be substituted for ECON 215 if STAT 218 was completed before declaring economics as a major; otherwise student must take ECON 215.

Completion of ECON 311 and ECON 312 is recommended before taking other 300- and 400-level courses.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Prerequisite Requirements/Rules

For all courses in the 300 series, junior standing and ECON 210 or ECON 211 are required with the exception of ECON 375, which has no prerequisite. ECON 211 and ECON 212 are required for ECON 303, ECON 311, ECON 312, ECON 321, ECON 340, ECON 388, and ECON 389. For all courses in the 400 series, except ECON 466 and ECON 467, junior standing and 12 hours in the social sciences including ECON 211 and ECON 212 are required as prerequisites. ECON 210 may be substituted for ECON 211 and ECON 212. Additional prerequisites may be in effect for some courses. See individual course listings.

Grade Rules

Pass/No Pass Limits

Any student in any college at UNL may not take business courses in the College of Business Administration using a Pass/No Pass option, unless otherwise stated.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Plan A: 18 hours

Plan B: 12 hours

Industrial & Management Systems Engineering

COLLEGE: Engineering

MAJOR: Industrial & Management Systems Engineering

DEGREE OFFERED: Bachelor of Science in Industrial Engineering

HOURS REQUIRED: 131

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: No

CHIEF ADVISER: Robert Williams

DESCRIPTION

Chair: Jeffrey C. Woldstad

Associate Chair: Robert E. Williams

Professors: Ballard, Bishu, Choobineh, Cochran, Hallbeck, Hoffman, Rajurkar, Riley, Woldstad

Associate Professors: Jones, Savory, Williams

Assistant Professor: Ko

Lecturer: Batur

The department offers a curriculum leading to the degree of bachelor of science in industrial engineering, designed to help prepare the student for a wide range of employment positions or further study. Industrial engineering involves the science and practice of designing and managing complex integrated systems. Industrial engineering education provides students with the background to participate in such activities as manufacturing engineering, ergonomics, production planning and control, economic analysis, statistical analysis, quality control, manpower planning, facilities design, packaging, robotics, computer simulation, work place design and analysis, inventory control and optimization.

Mission and Objectives

The mission of the department is to educate engineers, conduct research, and disseminate information to benefit the citizens of Nebraska and the nation. It is our educational goal to graduate outstanding engineers thoroughly trained in mathematics, basic sciences, engineering sciences, communications, computing, humanities, social sciences, engineering design and industrial engineering fundamentals, so that the graduates can enter the professional practice of engineering and perform at an exemplary level.

Our program educational objectives are:

Design, develop, implement and/or improve integrated systems that involve people, materials, machines, information, technology, processes, equipment, and/or financial resources.
Serve as effective change agents in the organizations that employ them, based on strong interpersonal and teamwork skills, an understanding of professional and ethical responsibility, and a willingness to take the initiative.
Able to use modern computer software tools to solve engineering problems and effectively communicate results, solutions, and/or recommendations.
Obtain professional employment and/or admission to a graduate education program.

ADMISSION

Major/Department Admission

4 units (or years) of college prep English
4 units of mathematics – algebra I, algebra II, geometry, pre-calculus, and trigonometry
3 units of social studies – 1 unit of American and/or world history and 1 unit of history, American government and/or geography
3 units of natural sciences – chemistry and physics, 1 unit must include laboratory
2 units of one foreign language

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Requirements for the Degree (Lincoln Campus)

First Semester Hours

CHEM 109 General Chemistry I 4

Can be substituted with CHEM 111 or CHEM 113.

ENGR 10 Freshman Engineering Seminar 0

IMSE 50 Intro to Industrial Engineering 0

MATH 106 Analytic Geometry & Calculus I 5

MECH 130 Intro to CAD 3

ACE Electives 6

Choose one course each from ACE outcomes 5, 6, 7, 8, and 9 elective courses.

Total 18

Second Semester Hours

MATH 107 Analytic Geometry & Calculus II 5

PHYS 211 General Physics I 4

ACE Electives 6

Choose one course each from ACE outcomes 5, 6, 7, 8, and 9 elective courses.

Total 15

Third Semester Hours

ENGM 223 Engineering Statics 3

ENGR 20 Sophomore Engineering Seminar 0

IMSE 206 Engineering Economy I 3

IMSE 275 Intro to Manufacturing Processes 3

MATH 208 Analytic Geometry & Calculus III 4

PHYS 212 General Physics II 4

Total 17

Fourth Semester Hours

CSCE 155 Computer Science I 4

Can be substituted with CSCE 150E (3 hr) and one of the following 1 hr courses: CSCE 251K or CSCE 252A.

ELEC 211 Elements of Electrical Engineering I 3

ELEC 231 Electrical Engineering Lab 1

IMSE 250 Intro to Industrial Systems 3

JGEN 200 Technical Communication I 3

MATH 221 Differential Equations 3

Total 17

Fifth Semester Hours

IMSE 305 Intro to Engineering Management 3

IMSE 315 Intro to Ergonomics 3

IMSE 321 Engr Statistics & Data Analysis 3

Engineering Science Elective 3

Engineering science electives total 6 hours. A student can choose from MECH 200 or MECH 310, ENGM 325 or ENGM 373, or METL 260.

ACE Elective 3

Choose one course each from ACE outcomes 5, 6, 7, 8, and 9 elective courses.

Total 15

Sixth Semester Hours

IMSE 328 Deterministic Operation Research Models 3

IMSE 334 Production & Operations Management 3

IMSE 375 Manufacturing Engineering 3

Information Systems Elective 3

Information systems electives total 3 hours. A student can choose from any CSCE course (except CSCE 101), ELEC 121, MATH 340/840, or MNGT 350, MNGT 452, MNGT 454, MNGT 456, MNGT 457, or MNGT 458.

Engineering Science Elective 3

Engineering science electives total 6 hours. A student can choose from MECH 200 or MECH 310, ENGM 325 or ENGM 373, or METL 260.

Communication Elective 3

Choose one course from the ACE SLO two elective courses.

Total 18

Seventh Semester Hours

IMSE 421 Applied Statistics & Quality Control 3

IMSE 428 Stochastic Operation Research Modeling 3

IMSE 440 Discrete Event Simulation 3

IMSE Elective I (select from following list) 3

IMSE Elective II (select from following list) 3

Total 15

Eighth Semester Hours

ENGR 400 Professional Ethics & Social Responsibilities 1

IMSE 434 Facility Planning & Design 3

IMSE 450 Senior Engineering Project 3

IMSE Elective I (select from following list) 3

IMSE Elective II (select from following list) 3

Technical Elective * 3

Total 16

* Three (3) credits of technical elective courses are to be selected by the student in conjunction with his/her adviser to formulate a coherent program in industrial engineering. A student can choose from any course in the IMSE Electives I and IMSE Electives II lists or a department-approved technical course at the sophomore level (200 level) or above from sciences, engineering, or mathematics.

Total Credit Hours Required 131

IMSE Electives I

IMSE 405 Analysis of Engineering Management

IMSE 406 Decision & Risk Analysis

IMSE 412 Occupation Safety – A Systems Analysis

IMSE 415 Cognitive Ergonomics

IMSE 416 Physical Ergonomics

IMSE 417 Occupational Safety Hygiene Engineering

IMSE 422 Industrial Quality Control

IMSE 476 Manufacturing Information Systems

IMSE Electives II

IMSE 460 Packaging Engineering

IMSE 461 RFID Systems in the Supply Chain

IMSE 470 Theory & Practice of Materials Processing

IMSE 471 Tool & Die Design

IMSE 475 Manufacturing Systems I

IMSE 477 Robotics

IMSE 483 Logistics in the Supply Chain

OTHER

Laboratories

Human Factors/Ergonomics Laboratory. Equipment in this facility includes an environmental chamber, oxygen consumption equipment for measuring physical work capacities, force-sensing resistors for grip studies, hand and pinch dynamometers, bicycle ergometer, and electromyography equipment of assessing localized muscle fatigue. Work focuses on assessing risk factors for cumulative trauma disorders in the hand and wrists and on human-computer interaction studies to evaluate user menus and interface design for manufacturing.

Innovative Design and Ergonomic Analysis (IDEA) Laboratory. The IDEA Lab employs usercentered design principles to design products, such as surgical tools or homeland security devices, that are intuitive to learn, easy to use and maintain by involving the end-users in the design process. The IDEA Lab also evaluates these products or those designed by others, such as a reduced size piano keyboard or computer mice, using subjective, usability and objective ergonomic testing, often employing the end-user. To perform the objective ergonomic testing, the IDEA Lab has custom designed equipment to study the movement of multiple joints such as the wrist and hand or the hand and forearm, touch screens to examine aiming capabilities, devices for force or torque measurement, anthropometry electromyography and electrogoniometry and a mock laparoscopic surgical suite.

Nontraditional Manufacturing Research Laboratory. The laboratory is the only facility of its kind in the United States studying advanced manufacturing processes. Advanced manufacturing equipment is needed to machine materials such as ceramics, super alloys, composites and tool steels used by the aerospace, automotive, electronics, and medical components industries. The advanced machining processes studies include electrodischarge machining, electrochemical machining, laser machining, abrasive waterjet machining, abrasive flow machining and ultrasonic machining. Work focuses on improving these advanced processes, developing computer-controlled systems, improving the surface integrity achieved with these processes, designing machine tools and applying the new processes to production of new complex parts while considering economics, safety, and the environment.

RFID and Supply Chain Logistics Laboratory. The laboratory is equipped with radio frequency identification (RFID) readers, tags, antennas and software. Warehouse management software, conveyor systems, retrieval systems and RFID training simulator are included.

Political Science

COLLEGE: Arts & Sciences

MAJOR: Political Science

DEGREES OFFERED: Bachelor of Arts or Bachelor of Science

HOURS REQUIRED: 125

MINIMUM CUMULATIVE GPA: 2.0 for graduation

MINOR AVAILABLE: Yes

CHIEF ADVISER: Tyler White

DESCRIPTION

Chair: Elizabeth Theiss-Morse, 509 Oldfather Hall

Graduate Chair: Patrice McMahon, 525 Oldfather Hall

Undergraduate Chair: John Gruhl, 534 Oldfather Hall

Undergraduate Adviser: Marcia White, 514 Oldfather Hall

Professors: Combs, Comer, Forsythe, Gruhl, Hibbing, Michaels, Smith, Theiss-Morse

Associate Professors: McMahon, Miller, Orey, Rapkin, Wedeman

Assistant Professors: Kohen, Mitchell, Tillman, Wagner

Courses in political science examine government and politics in the United States and around the world.

Honors Program. Students interested in the honors program should contact John Gruhl, honors adviser, for further information.

Policy Certificate. An Undergraduate Public Policy Analysis Certificate, through political science, is available to undergraduates in any major and is for students interested in policy issues, policy-related job opportunities, and/or skills for the analysis of public policies and programs. For more information, visit www.unl.edu/polisci/public/public_undergrad.html.

Prelaw Students. Students in Prelaw may find the courses in American government, politics, and law particularly useful. In particular, they are advised to take some of the following courses: POLS 325, POLS 345, POLS 350, POLS 441, POLS 442, POLS 443, and POLS 469. College pre-law advising is located in the Advising Center, 107 Oldfather Hall.

Graduate Work. The advanced degrees of master of arts and doctor of philosophy are offered. For details on these programs see the Graduate Studies Bulletin.

MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Specific Major Requirements

30 hours including:

a) POLS 100 or POLS 100H or POLS 105;

b) POLS 108 or POLS 380 or POLS 383 or POLS 384 or POLS 386;

c) POLS 400;

d) 6 hours each in any three of the five following categories: American government, politics and law; foreign and comparative government; international relations; political theory, methodology, and behavior; public administration and policy.

ADDITIONAL MAJOR REQUIREMENTS

Prerequisite Requirements/Rules

For courses at the 400 level the prerequisite, unless otherwise stated, is junior standing or above or permission.

Grade Rules

Pass/No Pass Limits

Pass/no pass credit is not available in courses for the major except for POLS 395. Pass/no pass credit is allowed for courses in the minor, subject to College regulations. Request forms are available in the Arts and Sciences Advising Center, 107 Oldfather Hall.

Course Level Requirement

At least 9 hours must be at the 400 level.

REQUIREMENTS FOR MINOR OFFERED BY DEPARTMENT

Plan A. 18 hours including POLS 100 and at least one course at the 400 level.

Plan B. 12 hours.